<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Psycho</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Alfred Hitchcock</name>
          <resp>Director</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Alfred Hitchcock</name>
          <resp>Producer</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Joseph Stefano</name>
          <resp>Screenplay</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Robert Bloch</name>
          <resp>Adaptation</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>John L. Russel</name>
          <resp>Director of Photography</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Bernard Herrmann</name>
          <resp>Music Composer</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Clarence Champagne</name>
          <resp>Special Effects</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Set Designer</resp>
          <name>Joseph Hurley</name>
          <name>Robert Claworthy</name>
          <name>George Milo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Sound Engineer</resp>
          <name>Walden O. Watson</name>
          <name>William Russell</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Saul Bass</name>
          <resp>Title Design</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>George Tomasini</name>
          <resp>Editor</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Hilton A. Green</name>
          <resp>Assistant Director</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Helen Colvig</name>
          <resp>Costumes</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent unit="minutes">109</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1960</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This TEI document was generated by converting an original screenplay, initially authored in a custom XML schema, into TEI format by the same creator, Farideh Sousani.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
        <p>This file was created as part of the Information Science and Cultural Heritage course project. It presents the screenplay of Psycho(1960) in a structured and standardized format using TEI.</p>
      </encodingDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <castList>
        <castItem>
          <roleName>Norman Bates</roleName>
          <actor>Anthony Perkins</actor>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <roleName>Lila Crane</roleName>
          <actor>Vera Miles</actor>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <roleName>Sam Loomis</roleName>
          <actor>John Gavin</actor>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <roleName>Milton Arbogast</roleName>
          <actor>Martin Balsam</actor>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <roleName>Al Chambers</roleName>
          <actor>John McIntire</actor>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <roleName alt="Dr. Simon">Dr. Richmond</roleName>
          <actor>Simon Oakland</actor>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <roleName>Mrs. Chambers</roleName>
          <actor>Lurene Tuttle</actor>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <roleName>Cassidy</roleName>
          <actor>Frank Albertson</actor>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <roleName>Caroline</roleName>
          <actor>Patricia Hitchcock</actor>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <roleName>Mr. Lowery</roleName>
          <actor>Vaughn Taylor</actor>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <roleName>Used Car Dealer</roleName>
          <actor>John Anderson</actor>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <roleName>Highway Patrolman</roleName>
          <actor>Mort Mills</actor>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <roleName>District Attorney</roleName>
          <actor>Francis De Sales</actor>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <roleName>Chief of Police</roleName>
          <actor>George Eldridge</actor>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <roleName alt="Mary">Marion Crane</roleName>
          <actor>Janet Leigh</actor>
        </castItem>
      </castList>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="scene" n="1">
        <head>EXT. PHOENIX, ARIZONA - DAY - HELICOPTER SHOT</head>
        <stage>
        Above Midtown section of the city. It is early afternoon, a hot mid-summer day.
        The city is sun-blanched white and its drifted-up noises are muted in their own echoes.
        We fly low, heading in a downtown direction, passing over traffic-clogged streets, parking lots, white business buildings, neatly patterned residential districts.
        As we approach downtown section, the character of the city begins to change.
        It is darker and shabby with age and industry.
        We see railroad tracks, smokestacks, wholesale fruit-and-vegetable markets, old municipal buildings, empty lots.
        The very geography seems to give us a climate of nefariousness, of back-doorness, dark and shadowy. And secret.
        </stage>
        <stage>
        We fly lower and faster now, as if seeking out a specific location.
        A skinny, high old hotel comes into view.
        On its exposed brick side great painted letters advertise "Transients - Low Weekly Rates - Radio in Every Room."
        We pause long enough to establish the shoddy character of this hotel...
        Its open, curtainless windows, its silent resigned look so characteristic of such hole-and-corner hotels.
        We move forward with purposefulness toward a certain window.
        The sash is raised as high as it can go, but the shade is pulled down to three or four inches of the inside sill, as if the occupants of the room within wanted privacy but needed air.
        We are close now, so that only the lower half of the window frame is in shot.
        No sounds come from within the room. Suddenly, we tip downward, go to the narrow space between shade and sill, peep into the room.
        </stage>
        <stage>
        A young woman is stretched out on the mussed bed. She wears a full slip, stockings, no shoes.
        She lies in and attitude of physical relaxation, but her face, seen in the dimness of the room, betrays a certain inner-tension, worrisome conflicts.
        She is Mary CRANE, an attractive girl nearing the end of her twenties and her rope.
        </stage>
        <stage>
        A man stands beside the bed, only the lower half of his figure visible.
        We hold on this tableau for a long moment, then start forward. As we pass under the window shade,
        </stage>
        <stage>CUT TO:</stage>
      </div>
      <div type="scene" n="2">
        <head>INT. HOTEL ROOM - (DAY)</head>
        <stage>
        A small room, a slow fan buzzing on a shelf above the narrow bed.
        A card of hotel rules is pasted on the mirror above the bureau.
        An unopened suitcase and a woman's large, straw open-top handbag are on the bureau.
        On the table beside the bed there are a container of Coca-Cola and an unwrapped, untouched egg-salad sandwich.
        There is no radio.
        </stage>
        <stage>
        The man standing by the bed, wearing only trousers, T-shirt and sox, is Sam LOOMIS, a good-looking, sensual shirt man with warm humorous eyes and a compelling smile.
        He is blotting his neck and face with a thin towel, and is staring down at Mary, a small sweet smile playing about his mouth.
        Mary keep her face turned away from him. After a moment, Sam drops the towel, sits on the bed, leans over and takes Mary into his arms, kisses her long and warmly, holds her with a firm possessiveness.
        The kiss is disturbed and finally interrupted by the buzzing closeness of an inconsiderate fly.
        Sam smiles, pulls away enough to allow Mary to relax again against the pillow.
        He studies her, frowns at her unresponsiveness, then speaks in a low, intimate, playful voice.
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>Never did eat your lunch, did you.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        Mary looks at his smile, has to respond, pulls him to her, kisses him.
        Then, and without breaking the kiss, she swings her legs over the side of the bed, toe-searches around, finds her shoes, slips her feet into searches them.
        And finally pulls away and sits up.
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>I better get back to the office. These extended lunch hours give my boss excess acid.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>Call your boss and tell him you're taking the rest of the afternoon off. It's Friday anyway... and hot.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>What do I do with my free afternoon, walk you to the airport?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>We could laze around here a while longer.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>Checking out time is three P.M. Hotels of this sort aren't interested in you when you come in, but when your time's up...</p>
          <p>Sam, I hate having to be with you in a place like this.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>I've heard of married couples who deliberately spend occasional nights in cheap hotels. They say it...</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>When you're married you can do a lot of things deliberately.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>You sure talk like a girl who's been married.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>Sam</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>I'm sorry, Mary.</p>
          <p>My old Dad used to say 'when you can't change a situation, laugh at it.' Nothing ridicules a thing like laughing at it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>I've lost my girlish laughter.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>The only girlish thing you have lost.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>Sam. This is the last time.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>For what?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>This! Meeting you in secret so we can be... secretive! You come down here on business trips and we steal lunch hours and... I wish you wouldn't even come.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>Okay. What do we do instead, write each other lurid love letters?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>I haven't time to argue. I'm a working girl.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>And I'm a working man! We're a regular working-class tragedy!</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>It is tragic! Or it will be... if we go on meeting in shabby hotels whenever you can find a tax-deductible excuse for flying down deductible here...</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>You can't laugh at it, huh?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>Can you?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>Sure. It's like laughing through a broken jaw, but...</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        He breaks off, his cheeriness dissolved, goes to the window, tries to raise the shade.
        It sticks.
        He pulls at it.
        It comes down entirely, and the hot sun glares into the room, revealing it in all its shabbiness and sordidness as if corroborating Mary's words and attitude.
        Sam kicks at the fallen shade, laughs in frustration, grabs on to his humor again.
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>And besides, when you say I make tax-deductible excuses you make me out a criminal.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        Marion exits a commercial building.
        Her demeanor is rushed.
        She glances around nervously and walks quickly to her parked car.
        </stage>
        <stage>
        She gets in, starts the engine, and pulls out into light traffic.
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>You couldn't be a criminal if you committed a major crime.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>I wish I were. Not an active criminal but... a nice guy with the conscience of a criminal.</p>
          <p>Next best thing to no conscience at all.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>I have to go, Sam.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>I can come down next week.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>No.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>Not even just to see you, to have lunch... in public?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>We can see each other, we can even have dinner... but respectably, in my house with my mother's picture on the mantel and my sister helping me broil a big steak for three!</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>And after the steak... do we send Sister to the movies and turn Mama's picture to the wall?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>Sam! No!</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>All right.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        She stares at him, surprised at his willingness to continue the affair on her terms, as girls are so often surprised when they discover men will continue to want them even after the sexual bait has been pulled in.
        Sam smiles reassuringly, places his hands gently on her arms, speaks with gentle and simple sincerity.
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>Mary, whenever it's possible, tax-deductible or not, I want to see deductible you. And under any conditions.</p>
          <p>Even respectability.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>You make respectability sound... disrespectful.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>I'm all for it! It requires patience and temperance and a lot of sweating-out... otherwise, though, it's only hard work.</p>
          <p>But if I can see you, touch you even as simply as this... I won't mind.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        He moves away and again the weight of his pain and problems crushes away his good humor.
        There is a quiet moment.
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>I'm fed up with sweating for people who aren't there. I sweat to pay off my father's debts... and he's in his grave... I sweat to pay my ex-wife alimony, and she's living on the other side of the world somewhere.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>I pay, too. They also pay who meet in hotel rooms.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>A couple of years and the debts will be paid off. And if she ever remarries, the alimony stops... and then...</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>I haven't even been married once yet!</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>Yeah, but when you do... you'll swing.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>Sam, let's go get married.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>And live with me in a storeroom behind a hardware store in Fairvale. We'll have a lot of laughs. When I send my ex-wife her money, you can lick the stamps.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>I'll lick the stamps.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        He looks at her, long, pulls her close, kisses her lightly, looks out the window and stares at the wide sky.
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>You know what I'd like? A clear, empty sky... and a plane, and us in it... and somewhere a private island for sale, where we can run around without our... shoes on. And the wherewithal to buy what I'd like.</p>
          <p>Mary, you want to cut this off, go out and find yourself someone available.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>I'm thinking of it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>How can you even think a thing like that!</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>Don't miss your plane.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Sam</speaker>
          <p>Hey, we can leave together can't we?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>I'm late... and you have to put your shoes on.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        Mary goes out quickly, closing door behind her.
        As Sam stares down at his shoeless feet,
        </stage>
        <stage>DISSOLVE TO:</stage>
      </div>
      <div type="scene" n="3">
        <head>EXT. DOWNTOWN STREET - (DAY) - HIGH ANGLE</head>
        <stage>
        Shooting down at hotel entrance. Mary comes out, walks quickly to a parked cab, gets in.
        The cab zooms up the awful street.
        </stage>
        <stage>DISSOLVE TO:</stage>
      </div>
      <div type="scene" n="4">
        <head>EXT. LOWERY REAL ESTATE OFFICE - (DAY)</head>
        <stage>
        A small, moderately successful office off the main street.
        A cab pulls up at the curb.
        We see Mary get out of cab, pay driver, cross pavement to the office door.
        </stage>
      </div>


      <div type="scene" n="5">
        <head>INT. OUTER OFFICE - (DAY)</head>
        <stage>
        Mary enters office, crosses to her desk, sits down, rubs her temples, finally looks over at Caroline, a girl in the last of her teens
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>Isn't Mr. Lowery back from lunch?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Caroline</speaker>
          <p>He's lunching with the man who's buying the Harris Street property, you know, that oil lease man... so that's why he's late.</p>
          <p>You getting a headache?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>It'll pass. Headaches are like resolutions... you forget them soon as they stop hurting.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Caroline</speaker>
          <p>You got aspirins? I have something... not aspirins, but my mother's doctor gave these to me the day of my wedding.</p>
          <p>Teddy was furious when he found out I'd taken tranquilizers!</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        She rises, starts for Mary's desk, pills in hand.
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>Were there any calls?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Caroline</speaker>
          <p>Teddy called. Me... And my mother called to see if Teddy called. Oh, and your sister called to say she's going to Tucson to do some buying and she'll be gone the whole weekend and...</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        She breaks off, distracted by the sound of the door opening.
        Mr. Lowery and his oil-lease client, Tom Cassidy, enter the office.
        Lowery is a pleasant, worried-faced man, big and a trifle pompous.
        Cassidy is loud and a bit drunk. He is gross, exuding pitiful vulgarity.
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Cassidy</speaker>
          <p>Wow! Hot as fresh milk! You girls should get your boss to air-condition you up. He can afford it today.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        Lowery flashes an embarrassed smile at Mary, tries to lead Cassidy toward the private office.
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Lowery</speaker>
          <p>Mary, will you get those copies of the deed ready for Mr. Cassidy.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        Cassidy pauses beside Mary's desk, hooks a haunch onto the desktop, smiles a wet smile at Mary.
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Cassidy</speaker>
          <p>Tomorrow's the day! My sweet little girl... Not you, my daughter! A baby, and tomorrow she stands up there and gets her sweet self married away from me!</p>
          <p>I want you to look at my baby. Eighteen years old... and she's never had an unhappy day in any one of those years!</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        Mary glances, cannot bring herself to smile or make a remark, continues sorting out the deed copies, tries to ignore the man's closeness.
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Lowery</speaker>
          <p>Come on, Tom, my office is air-conditioned.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Cassidy</speaker>
          <p>You know what I do with unhappiness? I buy it off! You unhappy?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mary</speaker>
          <p>Not inordinately.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Cassidy</speaker>
          <p>I'm buying this house for my baby's wedding present. Forty thousand dollars, cash! Now that ain't buying happiness, that's buying off unhappiness! That penniless punk she's marryin'... Probably a good kid... it's just that I hate him.</p>
          <p>Yup! Forty thousand, says here... Casharoonie!</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        He takes two bundles of new $100 bills from his pocket and throws them onto the desk under Mary's nose.
        Caroline's eyes go wide. Cassidy leans close, flicks through the bills, laughs.
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Cassidy</speaker>
          <p>I never carry more than I can afford to lose!</p>
          <p>Count 'em!</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Lowery</speaker>
          <p>Tom... cash transactions of this size! Most irregular...</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Cassidy</speaker>
          <p>So what? It's my private money! And now it's yours.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Caroline</speaker>
          <p>I declare!</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Cassidy</speaker>
          <p>I don't! That's how I'm able to keep it!</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Lowery</speaker>
          <p>Suppose we just put this in the safe and then Monday morning when you're feeling good...</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Cassidy</speaker>
          <p>Speakin' of feeling good, where's that bottle you said you had in your desk... Oops! Usually I can keep my mouth shut!</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        He rises, reels toward Lowery's office, pauses, turns, speaks to Mary.
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Cassidy</speaker>
          <p>Honest. I can keep any private transaction a secret... any pri....</p>
          <p>Lowery! I'm dyin' of thirstaroonie!</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        Lowery starts after him, pauses, turns to Mary.
        Cassidy has gone into Lowery's office.
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Lowery</speaker>
          <p>I don't even want it in the office over the weekend. Put it in the safe deposit box, at the bank, Mary. And we'll get him to give us a check on Monday - instead.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        He hurries off.
        When the men are gone and the door is closed, Caroline picks up a bundle and smiles at it.
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Caroline</speaker>
          <p>He was flirting with you. I guess he noticed my wedding ring.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage>
        Mary puts one bundle into a large envelope and takes the other from Caroline.
        She puts the envelope in her handbag, picks up the remaining deed copies, goes to the private office door, knocks, starts to open it as...
        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Lowery</speaker>
          <p>Come in.</p>
        </sp>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
